Guide to the Sydney Nathans Collection, 1975-2018 UA.29.02.0130
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sydney Nathans collection
1975-2018 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nathans, Sydney
UA.29.02.0130
3.5 Linear Feet 5 boxes; 1 oversize folder
The papers in this collection include Duke history professor Sydney Nathans' documentation on the Richard Nixon Presidential Library debate, including his participation in Academic Council resolutions regarding the location of the library on Duke's campus; the Greensboro Massacre (1979), when the Ku Klux Klan murdered several people during a shoot-out at an Anti-KKK demonstration planned by the Communist Workers' Party; Nathans' copies of negatives and contact sheets from the Durham bicentennial photography project (1981 and undated); and materials used in the writing of his book A Mind to Stay, including original interviews, transcripts, and other research materials.
Access Restrictions
Use of audiotapes and videotapes from this collection requires the creation of reference copies. Reference copies for some materials may have been made, and if a reference copy exists, it is noted in this finding aid. To arrange for the creation of reference copies of other items, please contact University Archives staff. Although these recordings are now stored in a stable environment, their condition and playback quality is unknown.
Provenance
The Sydney Nathans Collection was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1985. A Rubenstein Library-held portion of the papers was merged with the University Archives collection in 2017 to form one Sydney Nathans Papers. Another gift was received in 2018.
Biographical/Historical note
Sydney Nathans is a Professor Emeritus in the Duke University History Department. He has written several books on United States history and the lives of African Americans, including To Free a Family: The Journey of Mary Walker and A Mind to Stay: White Plantation, Black Homeland. He is a fellow of John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, and was born in 1940.
Greensboro Massacre
A shoot-out between the Ku Klux Klan and the Communist Workers' Party during a Death to the Klan march on Nov. 3, 1979, led to the death of five anti-Klan demonstrators in Greensboro, N.C. Subsequent criminal trials led to the acquittals of several KKK and American Nazi Party members; a later civil suit found the Klan and the Greensboro Police Department liable for failing to prevent violence.
Nixon Presidential Library
In July 1981, Terry Sanford initiated negotiations with former U. S. President Richard Nixon (Duke Law '37) to locate the Nixon presidential library on the campus of Duke University, Nixon's alma mater. When this information was revealed to faculty members during the week of August 10, 1981, many opposed the proposition, citing Sanford's failure to consult the faculty prior to initiating negotiations.
Many who opposed the library had moral objections to memorializing a President whose behavior in office was reproachable, and they feared a negative effect on the university's reputation. Other concerns included the effects of increased tourist traffic on campus and the uncertain aesthetic nature of the proposed structure. However, supporters of the Nixon Library argued that the scholarly and academic benefits of locating the Nixon Presidential Materials collection on campus should and would outweigh other concerns. These supporters tended to denounce the actions of vocal dissenters as divisive and arrogant. To learn more about these and other issues concerning the potential impact on Duke of the proposed Nixon Library, Professor Sydney Nathans researched modern presidential libraries. His findings were presented to members of the Duke Academic Council as well as the Board of Trustees, and he based his own formal statement in August of 1981 to the Council on these findings.
Meetings of the Academic Council and Board of Trustees during September and October 1981 were dominated by the Nixon Library debate, and a group of faculty formed the Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library (CANDL) to organize the efforts of faculty, students, alumni, and others opposed to the proposed library. Although the Academic Council voted not to pursue further negotiations with former president Nixon in a 35-34 decision at a September 3, 1981 meeting, the Board of Trustees later voted 9-2 to proceed. By April 1982, negotiations had stalled. One year later, Nixon's representatives announced that a site at Chapman College in San Clemente, California, had been chosen for the Richard M. Nixon Presidential Library.
Scope and Contents note
The Nixon Library papers contain correspondence (including that of Terry Sanford, and of the creator of the collection, Sydney Nathans); newspaper and magazine clippings as well as scholarly articles; text from speeches; official statements from groups opposing the Nixon Library; and Sydney Nathan's handwritten notes from a variety of meetings. Documents also include Nathan's research on existing presidential libraries.
The Greensboro Massacre papers contain flyers and other mailings and newsletters from the Communist Workers Party and other socialist organizations; mailings from Greensboro Justice Fund and other sympathetic groups following the massacre; media and press coverage of the massacre and the subsequent trials; a police report from Greensboro's police chief; academic and other literature researching the history of violence between the Communist and Klan organizations; and other miscellaneous materials.
The Durham Bicenntenial photography project relates to a project now held in the Durham Arts Council and consists of negatives and contact sheets for a photographic history of Durham assembled in 1981.
The A Mind to Stay Interviews and Transcripts contain materials used by Sydney Nathans in writing his book A Mind to Stay: White Plantation, Black Homeland, on the descendants of enslaved families forced to migrate from North Carolina to plantations in Greensboro, Alabama, and Tunica, Mississippi, in 1844, and the communities those families formed in the following years. Materials include recordings of interviews with residents of the two towns, Nathans' transcripts and extensive notes of those interviews, photos of interviewees and local landmarks, background material and research, the text of speeches and eulogies, and Nathans' personal correspondence with historians, editors, and Greensboro, Alabama, residents.
Related Material
Nixon Library Controversy collection.
University Archives, Duke University.
Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library (CANDL).
University Archives, Duke University.
Presidential libraries -- United States; Durham (N.C.) -- Pictorial works; Greensboro (N.C.) -- Demonstration, 1979; Labor movement -- United States; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994 -- Public opinion; Nathans, Sydney; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Duke University. Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library; Duke University. Board of Trustees; Sanford, Terry; Duke University. Academic Council; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University -- Alumni and alumnae; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- North Carolina; Communist Workers Party (U.S.)
- Nixon Presidential Library controversy, 1970s-1982 and undated
  - H.G. Jones: "Presidential Libraries" (Box 1)
  - Nixon-University Committee for an Enormous Shrine (NUKES), undated (Box 1)
  - Colleagues Against Any Backsliding at All (CAABALL), 1982 (Box 1)
  - National Archives and Record Services conversations, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Francis Loewenheim Article (Box 1)
  - Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library (CANDL), 1981 (Box 1)
  - Trustee Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Alumni/Alumnae Letter from Terry Sanford, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Presidential Libraries: Bibliographies, 1975-1980s (Box 1)
  - Time Magazine Article on Nixon Library, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Nathans Correspondence: Miscellaneous, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Select Committee Tasks, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Notes on Donald L. Horowitz Talk at Nixon Library Teach-In, 1981 (Box 1)
  - James David Barber: On Nixon, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Presidential Libraries: Correspondence and Conversation at Duke, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Trustee Resolution, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Nixon Library: Miscellaneous, 1981 and undated (Box 1)
  - Ford Museum Article, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Letters, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Nixon Library News Stories, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Presidential Library Expenses, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Dellinger and Van Alstyne on Nixon Library, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Access to Nixon Papers, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Hoover Library Grant-in-Aid Program, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Theodore Ropp, "Teaching Tainted History", 1981 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Correspondence from Nathans, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Notes of Meeting, Concerned Faculty, undated (Box 1)
  - Letters from Faculty to Terry Sanford, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Watson-Sanford Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Terry Sanford Communications, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Anne Scott: NY Times Article, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Articles on USC Role in Nixon Library Debate, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Misc Documents For and Against the Nixon Library, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees Materials, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Local News Articles, Nixon Library Debate, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Articles on Accessibility and Ownership of Presidential Papers, 1970s-1981 (Box 1)
  - Nixon Library Summary, 1981 and undated (Box 1)
  - Statement to the Academic Council (Sydney Nathans), 1981 (Box 1)
- Greensboro Massacre materials, 1978-1985
  - Administrative report of the Anti-KKK Rally, Greensboro, N.C., written by William Swing, Chief of Police, Greensboro, 1979 Nov. 19 (Box 2)
  - Greensboro Justice Fund, 1982 and undated (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Newsletters, mailings
  - Massacre coverage in the press, 1979-1980; 4 folders (Box 2)
    Newspaper clippings/excerpts from sources including Durham Sun, Coal Field Defender, Duke Chronicle, North Carolina Anvil, Greensboro Daily News
  - Post-massacre, trial coverage in the press, 1979-1985; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Newspaper clippings from various sources, including: Daily Tar Heel, Greensboro Daily News, Durham Morning Herald, NC Independent
  - Massacre coverage: note cards tracing news coverage (Box 3)
  - Ku Klux Klan activities/press coverage, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    Profiles in media outlets of Klan activities, including marches.
  - Communist Workers Party newspapers, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Communists/socialists/workers party newspapers, press, 1980 (Box 2)
    Assorted issues of various left-wing and radical newspapers covering labor and pro-Communist and Socialist activities and beliefs
  - Greensboro-related flyers for assorted events, topics, 1980 and undated (Box 2)
  - Greensboro Massacre book drafts, by Paul and Sandy Bermanzohn, 1980 (Box 2)
  - A Group of Concerned Triangle Area Citizens, 1980 and undated (Box 2)
    Flyers, newsletters, and circulars
  - Death to Klan flyers, undated (Box 3)
    From the International Committee Against Racism of the Progressive Labor Party
  - Communist-related flyers and mailings, 1980s and undated (Box 3)
  - Academic papers re: communism in America (various students and authors), 1979 and undated (Box 3)
  - Michael Nathan commemorative poster (Oversize-folder 1)
- Durham Bicentennial photographs project, 1981 and undated
  - Durham Bicentennial photographs project, 1981 and undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
    Reproduced negatives and contact sheets of historic Durham photographs, gathered for the Durham bicentennial in 1981. Index included.
- A Mind To Stay Interviews and Transcripts, 1965-2018
  The A Mind to Stay Interviews and Transcripts series relates to Nathans' research on the descendants of families forced to migrate from North Carolina to plantations in Greensboro, Alabama, and Tunica, Mississippi, in 1844, and the communities those families formed in the following years, used to write his 2017 book, A Mind to Stay. The series contains: recordings of interviews with residents of the two towns, conducted between 1978 and 1988, primarily relating to family and local history with particular reference to the Emancipation and the Civil Rights Movement periods; Nathans' transcripts and extensive notes of those interviews; photos of interviewees and local landmarks; background material and research regarding the history of the Greensboro, Alabama, region, including 1964-1965 clippings from local paper the Greensboro Watchman and notes on Nathan Bedford Forrest, the plantations on which the families worked, and local political history; the text of speeches and eulogies related to this research; and Nathans' personal correspondence with historians, editors, and Greensboro, Alabama, residents.
  Nathans arranged the majority of the transcripts and supplementary material alphabetically by person interviewed, including supplementary material pertaining to voting rights struggles and other materials. Audiocassette titles were transcribed as closely as possible and are integrated into alphabetical order as much as possible, but many tapes include interviews with more than one person.
  Sydney Nathans' description of the materials and original inventory are included in Box 4 (Box 1 in Nathans' inventory).
  - Inventory and summary description by Sydney Nathans, 2018 (Box 4)
  - Banks: Angeline Banks Interviews, 1978-1986 (Box 4)
  - Banks: York Banks Interviews, 1980-1983 (Box 4)
  - Banks: York and Matilda Banks, undated (Box 4)
  - Banks: York, Tilda, and Arie Banks Interviews, 1980-2010 (Box 4)
  - Angeline Banks, 1978 August 20; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0109)
  - Elijah Banks, 1981 November 22; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0082)
  - York Banks; Cassimore Service, 1983 July 1, 1983 July 3; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0120)
  - Angeline Banks and Minnie Washington, 1983 June 24; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0083)
  - Elijah Banks; Gates Rainer, 1983 June 24; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0086)
  - Angeline Banks; Louis Rainey, 1983 June 26-27; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0085)
  - Angeline Banks and Minnie Washington, 1986 December 21; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0081)
  - Cassimore Service; Angeline Banks; Louie Rainey, 1986 July 8; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0089)
  - Lewis Black: Interviews, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Lewis Black: 1967, 1972 Interviews (Box 4)
  - Lewis Black: Schematic Notes, 2010-2015 (Box 4)
  - Lewis Black: 2010 Interview Notes, 2009-2010 (Box 4)
  - Lewis Black: Chronology, 2011 (Box 4)
  - Lewis Black: Trial Report, 1965, 2011 (Box 4)
  - Lewis Black: 1930 Federal Census, 1930, 2011 (Box 4)
  - Lewis Black: Flyer, undated (Box 4)
  - Lewis Black: Class Action, 1970-1972, 2011 (Box 4)
  - Lewis Black: Lewis and Mildred Election Results, 1974, 2011 (Box 4)
  - Post-Movement Around Greene, Lowndes, Turner, 1993, 2000, 2010 (Box 4)
  - Lewis Black, 1981 November 24; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0030)
  - Lewis Black; Notes on Mary Ellen Hayes, 1981 November 24; audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0065)
  - Lewis Black, 1983 June 22; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0031)
  - Martin Bond, 1981 May 15; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0157)
  - Ernst Borinski, 1982 July; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0084)
  - Burrell, Velva: Alabama Genealogy, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Cabbil: Lem Cabbil Interviews, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Cabbil: Aunt Mandy, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Cabbil: Robert Cabbil, 1979-1983 (Box 4)
  - Cabbil: Maggie Cabbil, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Cabbil: Mary Cabbil, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Cabbil Family Reunion, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Cabbil: Robert Cabbil Schematic Notes, 2010 (Box 4)
  - Lim Cabbil #3, 1983 June 29; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0087)
  - Cannon: James Cannon, 1983-2013 (Box 4)
  - Cannon: Tom Cannon, 1980 (Box 4)
  - James and Lillie Mae Cannon; Dan Rainer; Lewis Black, 1983 June 21; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0032)
  - Carrie Davis Interview, with Joel Wallace, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Carey Davis; Elmina Willis, 1981 November 23; audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0038)
  - Joel Wallace and Carrie Davis, 1983 June 22; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0088)
  - Bob Davis, 1986 July 5; audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0037)
  - Rev. A. T. Days, 2011 (Box 4)
  - Isaac Field, 1981 April 17; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0145)
  - Mirrie Hargrow; Isaac Field and Wife, 1981 April 17; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0156)
  - Isaac Field and Wife Tunica, 1981 April 18; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0146)
  - Isaac Field and Wife, 1981 November 4; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0092)
  - Isaac Field and Wife, 1981 November 4; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0104)
  - Flagg Family: Raleigh, 1988; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0022)
  - James Flagg et al, 1981 May 1; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0147)
  - James Flagg et al (Tape 1), 1981 May 1; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0149)
  - Frank and Cecil Flagg, 1988 October 14; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0021)
  - John Hope Franklin; Plessy vs. Ferguson, undated; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0023)
  - Cliff Granberry, 1981 April 23; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0154)
  - Rev. Robert Grant, 1981 April 16; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0136)
  - Rev. Robert Grant (Tape 1), 1981 April 16; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0153)
  - Carroll Greenhill Tape, undated; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0095)
  - Alice Hargress Correspondence, 1978-1984 (Box 4)
  - Hargress Family Bible, undated (Box 4)
  - Alice Hargress Interviews, 1978-1980 (Box 4)
  - Alice Hargress, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Alice Hargress, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Alice Hargress: Demonstration, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Alice Hargress: Notes and Interviews, 1978, 2011, 2015 (Box 4)
  - Alice Hargress: Correspondence, 2006-2009 (Box 4)
  - Cassimore Album, 2008 (Box 4)
  - Alice Hargress: 95th Birthday, 2009 (Box 4)
  - Alice Hargress: Death and Eulogy, 2014 (Box 4)
  - David Hargress, 2016 (Box 4)
  - Nathan Bedford Forrest: Descendents, undated (Box 4)
  - Nathan Bedford Forrest: Ambrose Hargress, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Nathan Bedford Forrest: Richard Jones, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Ambrose Hargress: Affadavit, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Forrest Hargress, undated (Box 4)
  - Richard Jones, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Nathan Bedford Forrest: Articles, 1908-1942 (Box 4)
  - Ambrose Hargress, 1988 July 5 (Box 4)
  - Earle Hargress, 1988 July 4 (Box 4)
  - Ned F. Hargress, 1980-1988 (Box 4)
  - Porch Interview: Hargress, Washington, et. al., 1978 August 18; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0002)
  - Alice Hargress; Elijah Banks; B. Washington; M. Williams, 1978 August 19; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0008)
  - Alice Hargress, 1978 August 20; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0010)
  - Ned F. Hargress II, 1981 December 21; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0108)
  - Alice Hargress; Louis Rainey, 1983 June 20; audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0064)
  - Alice Hargress and Cabbil, Tape 1, 1983 June 20; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0090)
  - Alice Hargress and Angeline Banks, 1983 June 25-26; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0079)
  - Ambrose Hargress, 1988 July 5; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0026)
  - Alice Hargress, 1988 July 6; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0024)
  - Mary Ellen Ruffin Hayes, 1981-1983 (Box 4)
  - Mary Ellen Ruffin and Carol Hayes: Interview, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Mary Ellen Ruffin and Carol Hayes: Notes and Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
  - Betty Hayes, Beulah Suitt; Margaret Umstead, 1981; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0027)
  - Carol and Maryellen Ruffin Hayes, 1981 May 22; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0029)
  - Mary Ellen Ruffin Hayes, 1981 May 22; audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0067)
  - Mary Ellen Ruffin Hayes, 1981 May 22; audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0068)
  - Betty Hayes: Stagville Talk, 1982 June; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0028)
  - Mary Ellen Hayes; Freetown; Lim Cabbil, 1983 June 30; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0073)
  - Mary Ellen Hayes; Joseph Phillips, 1983 June 30-July 1; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0074)
  - Johnny Brittain Henderson, 1981 November 14; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0137)
  - Johnny Brittain Henderson; Sherman Huening, 1981 November 14; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0148)
  - Andrew Fennell (Preacher); Johnny Britain Henderson, 1981 November 14; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0150)
  - Sherman Heoing, 1981 November 14; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0133)
  - Rev. Clemmie Humphries; Nell Johnson, 1981 November 12; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0140)
  - Clemmie Humphries, 1981 November 13; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0138)
  - Clemmie Humphries, 1981 November 13; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0139)
  - Nellie Johnson Tape 1, 1981 April 29; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0141)
  - Nellie Johnson Tape 2, 1981 April 29; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0142)
  - Nell Johnson, 1981 November 12; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0143)
  - Richard Jones, 1981 November 15; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0144)
  - Stagville Program: Alice Jones, 1986 February 22; audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0060)
  - Otis Lumpkin and Frank Kittle, 1981 November 4; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0131)
  - Frank Kittle, 1981 November 9; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0130)
  - Robert Lloyd; Cleveland (Tunica), 1982 May; audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0047)
  - Robert Lloyd, undated; audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0048)
  - Otis Lumpkin, 1981 November 9; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0135)
  - Lyles: James and Eliza Interviews, 1979-1981 (Box 4)
  - Lyles: James and Eliza Notes, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Lyles: Farmer's Club, undated (Box 4)
  - Lyles: Civil Rights, 2015 (Box 4)
  - Lyles: James Interview Notes, 2009 (Box 4)
  - Lyles: Gene Interview, 2014 June (Box 4)
  - Lyles: Eugene Interview Notes, 1979-2010 (Box 4)
  - Lyles: Rosie (Hale Ballot Changes), 2006-2010 (Box 4)
  - Lyles: Ala. Literacy Test, undated (Box 4)
  - Lyles: Voter Dispite, 2011 (Box 4)
  - James and Eliza Lyles, 1983 June 21; audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0069)
  - Jessie Parker (1 of 3), 1981 April 27; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0011)
  - Jessie Parker (2 of 3), 1981 April 27; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0012)
  - Jessie Parker (3 of 3), 1981 April 27; audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0013)
  - Jesse Parker, 1981 November 2; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0105)
  - Jesse Parker, 1981 November 2; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0106)
  - Harold Parker Talk, Senior Honors Seminar, 1983 March 18; audiocassette (Box 9, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0121)
  - Harold Parker Senior Seminar, 1985 November 10; audiocassette (Box 10, Audio-cassette UA29020130-CS-0159)
  - Joseph Phillips, 1983 (Box 4)